Algorithm.
I'm sure you've heard that word before.
It's used all over and it's so important in programming.
But what exactly is an algorithm and what does it do?
So in this lesson we're going to uncover some more of these mysteries.
And we'll also implement a simple algorithm in our game.
So first things first what is an algorithm.
Well imagine you're following a specific recipe to bake a cake or playing a new game that has a set
of rules to follow.
That's kind of what an algorithm is.
It's like a recipe or a set of rules that computers follow to do something cool.
So that said, how do computers use algorithms?
Well, you know, when you type something into Google and get a list of web pages, that's an algorithm
helping find those pages for you?
Or have you ever noticed how a website can show you items in order of price, from lowest to highest?
That's an algorithm tool.
Or in video games, algorithms can help control what the other characters do and decide the outcome
of certain actions.
They're used almost everywhere, from YouTube to Netflix to TikTok to Amazon.
So now that you have some kind of idea on what algorithms are, let's discuss the algorithm we are going
to build in our game.
We're going to have an algorithm in our game called the Safe Path algorithm, and it plays a crucial
role in making the game both challenging and playable.
So how does it work?
We start with a rectangle sprite positioned at the top of the screen.
Then the rectangle moves slowly to the left or right across the screen.
And as the rectangle moves, it prevents trees from appearing in its current position, and this action
creates a safe path for the player.
So that said, why is it considered an algorithm?
Well, there are three reasons.
Sequential steps.
The algorithm involves specific steps executed in order positioning the rectangle, its movement, and
the blocking tree.
Secondly, decision making the random movement of the rectangle requires decision making processes and
determining which direction to move at any given moment.
And thirdly, problem solving.
The main issue here is to preventing the player from being trapped by trees, and the safe path algorithm
addresses this by always clearing a path.
So basically, the safe path algorithm ensures there is always an open route for the player to move,
avoiding an unplayable situation, which wouldn't really be fair in our game.
The player can continue moving forward, navigating through the obstacles, making the gameplay experience
both fair and engaging.
Now, in the essence, the algorithm balances the game.
It ensures that it's challenging on the one side, yet it's also obviously possible to navigate, so
this enriches and enhances the whole playing experience.
Now, while I will be building this, I'm going to go at a very fast pace as we won't be using this
in our game as we continue.
This lesson is more to help you understand an important programming concept.
However, you can still use it if you'd like to change the dynamics of your game a bit, you can still
apply this.
Okay, so first things first, we need our rectangle sprite and the sprite is simple enough.
We can just hit paint button.
Then in the editor we can just select this tool.
And then just draw a simple rectangle like so.
We can adjust the size a bit so it looks something like this.
Then going into the code all we have to do is grab a win, start a forever a glide and a pick random
which we will stick under the X input.
And we'll change the pick random to -220 to 220, and we can set Y to 180.
Now, if we play, you will see we have this box that goes from one side of the screen to the other.
So now that we have the movement, we need one more thing, which is to report the position.
And we do this to make sure that the other sprites can know what position our rectangle sprite in is
at all times.
So all we need to do is duplicate the script, remove the glide, and move over to our other variables
and create a new one which we will call Safe Path.
Now we can grab this set into our forever loop.
Change it to save path.
And we're going to set our safe path to our X position.
So now our sprite moves.
It constantly sets this variable to its current position.
Now remember how I said an algorithm is kind of like baking a cake, or playing a game where you need
to follow instructions or rules.
So this is our instructions or rules.
So our trees aren't allowed to spawn in the location of our algorithm sprite.
So now all we need to do is make sure that the tree sprites follow these rules.
So moving over to the sprite.
If you look at the script here, as you can see, our trees are just going to a random X position.
So to fix this we are going to grab a repeat until block and insert it right over here.
Then we can duplicate this bit here and put this go to block inside our repeat until.
So finally what we want is to keep changing our X position until we are not in the path of our rectangle.
So to do this, we're going to need a few blocks which are a greater than, a lesser than and a or a
plus a minus two of our safe path variables.
And finally our two of our X positions.
And how we want to connect is just like this.
Yeah, I know this may have been a bit confusing, but let's run through the code so our trees spawn
in a random x position.
Then we have this part.
So if our tree's current x position is within 100 pixels to the left of our safe path, then it needs
to try again.
Or if our trees are 100 pixels to the right, it also has to try again.
And if they are not in the path of the sprite, it will continue.
So you see this in action.
We can quickly go to our variable sprite, disconnect this over here and change our spawn rate to zero.
Then under our safe path sprite we can hide it.
Now clicking play.
There you can see a bunch of trees spawning, yet we still have a safe path to follow.
So yeah, that's algorithms in a nutshell.
I know this lesson was pretty fast paced, so don't worry if you weren't able to follow along because
as I said, this lesson is more to give you a simple understanding of an important concept.
But for a game, we won't be using this algorithm as we continue.
But if you'd like to use it, you are more than welcome.